A Guide to the Records of the Charlottesville School Board 1869-2006
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Series I: Desegregation
  - A. Correspondence
    - Letter from Parents of "Negro" students applying to "white schools" [1958], 1 item (Box-folder 1:44)
      Parents requested admission of their children to public schools without regard to race or color.
    - Letters from Fendall R. Ellis to J. J. Brewbaker, Superintendent of Norfolk Schools and Frank Gregg about the Charlottesville School Board Resolution and district maps 1958 August 4, 4 items (Box-folder 1:45)
      Superintendent Ellis sent Superintendent Brewbaker a copy of the resolution (desegregation plan see 1:38). There are also minutes from the School Board meeting of July 8, 1958, a description of the Charlottesville School Districts, a letter thanking Gregg for maps of the school districts.
    - Letter from Fendall R. Ellis to John S. Battle, Jr. about the applications of "Negro" children to "white schools." 1958 August 14, 1 item (Box-folder 1:46)
      Superintendent Ellis wrote that he was afraid that if they desegregated, the schools would be closed.
    - Letter from Fendall R. Ellis to the members of the School Board 1958 August 14, 1 item (Box-folder 1:47)
      Superintendent Ellis wrote to the School Board that there was no change in the status of the segregation case and informed them of the schedule for testing and interviewing the applicants.
    - Letter from Fendall R. Ellis to John S. Battle, Jr. about the interviews with the parents of "Negro" students 1958 August 19, 1 item (Box-folder 1:48)
      Ellis wrote that it might be better to handwrite the notes during the interviews using shorthand as opposed to using recordings. He wrote that recordings might look like "the trappings of a Congressional investigation" and also that the Judge might "look with some skepticism on this technique."
    - Letter from Governor James Lindsay Almond, Jr. to the Superintendents of Virginia Schools 1958 September 4, 1 item (Box-folder 1:49)
      Governor Almond issued a statement explaining that no child could be excluded from school on a racial basis due to the Supreme Court ruling but no one had the authority to force a child to attend an integrated school.
    - Letter from Fendall R. Ellis to Thomas J. Michie congratulating him on his position as Mayor of Charlottesville 1958 Sept 16, 1 item (Box-folder 1:50)
      Dr. Ellis wrote, "I want to tell you how gratified I am that you are serving as the head of the city government during this difficult period."
    - Letter from Governor James Lindsay Almond, Jr. to the Charlottesville School Board ordering the closing of Lane and Venable Schools, 1 item (Box-folder 1:51)
      The Governor wrote "Under compulsion of an order issued by the United States District Court for the Western District of Virginia, both white and colored children have been enrolled effective September 22, 1958 in Lane High School and Venable Elementary School. Pursuant to the provisions of Chapter 9.1, Title 22, of the Code of Virginia, the above-named schools are closed…"
    - Letters from Fendall R. Ellis to School Board members and teachers at Lane and Venable Schools 1958 September 22, 3 items (Box-folder 1:52)
      Superintendent Ellis wrote about the resolution that parents should make private arrangements for education, and that teacher contracts would not be jeopardized by the closed schools.
    - Letter from Fendall R. Ellis to James Harry Michael, Jr. regarding Supreme Court's "proclamation" of September 29 (not present) 1958 October 1, 1 item (Box-folder 1:53)
    - Letters from Fendall R. Ellis and John S. Battle, Jr., about the legal interpretation of Judge John Paul's order 1958 October 13, 2 items (Box-folder 1:54)
      The letters are to the School Board and teachers at Venable and Lane, and to R. Stanley Goodman explaining that teachers were not permitted to teach in private segregated classrooms using state funds, according to the Judge's ruling.
    - Letters between John S. Battle, Jr. and Fendall R. Ellis about signatures on the appeal bond 1958 October 21, 2 items (Box-folder 1:55)
      Mr. Battle advised Superintendent Ellis that R. Stanley Goodman and Dr. Ellis needed to sign the appeal bond before a notary public.
    - Letters from Fendall R. Ellis to Superintendents J. J. Brewbaker and Ray E. Reid about the 1870 Act of Congress 1958 November 13, 6 items (Box-folder 1:56)
      Superintendent Ellis wrote in confidence about the 1870 Act of Congress which stipulated that the General Assembly had to maintain public schools in the state.
    - Letters from Fendall R. Ellis to Frederick L. Morton and Mrs. Paul L. Carr about the First Baptist Church and the Joint High School Committee 1958 November 17, 24, 2 items (Box-folder 1:57)
      Superintendent Ellis wrote about using and cleaning the Youth Building.
    - Correspondence between Fendall R. Ellis and James E. Bowen about night watchmen during the school crisis 1958 November 18, 24, 2 items (Box-folder 1:58)
      City Manager, James E. Bowen recommended that watchmen be placed on duty until the school crisis was over and Ellis responded that watchman were being placed at Lane, Venable and Burley at all times when the schools were closed.
    - Letter from Davis Y. Paschell to Fendall R. Ellis giving permission to have basketball practice and games 1958 November 21, 1 item (Box-folder 1:59)
      Davis Y. Paschell, Superintendent of Public Instruction approved the request and wrote that the Governor had allowed permission for sports in other closed schools in Norfolk and Warren County.
    - Letter from Fendall R. Ellis to John S. Battle, Jr. about an article by David Lawrence on the Fourteenth Amendment (not present) 1958 December 4, 1 item (Box-folder 1:60)
      Superintendent Ellis sent Mr. Battle a copy of an article which suggested that the Fourteenth Amendment was never passed.
    - Letter from Fendall R. Ellis to [Daniel] J. Meador, Law School Professor and School Board minutes about the resolution for desegregation 1958 December 9, 2 items (Box-folder 1:61)
    - Letter and news clippings from Fendall R. Ellis to Edmund Baxter about a statement on school closings 1958 December 9, 7 items (Box-folder 1:62)
      Included is Arthur Fleming's statement about the serious disadvantages of children being without schools. Both Baxter and Fleming were officials with the Department of Health, Education and Welfare.
    - Letter from John S. Battle, Jr. to the members of the School Board regarding the Harrison-Day Case and a letter about the re-opening of schools 1959 January 23, 3 items (Box-folder 1:63)
      Mr. Battle advised that since they had lost all of their appeals, they had to allow "Negro" students admission into Venable and Lane schools. The School Board was given the authority to open the schools and Ellis received praise for their re-opening.
    - Letters between Fendall R. Ellis and Edmund Baxter concerning the school crisis and a report on the impact of school closings 1959 February 3, 4 items (Box-folder 1:64)
      Superintendent Ellis wrote that he felt that the school situation was "moving toward a reasonable solution."
    - Letters between Fendall R. Ellis, Ray E. Reid, and J. J. Brewbaker about the success during the first day that schools were opened 1959 February 3, 4 items (Box-folder 1:65)
    - Letter from Attorney General Albertis S. Harrison, Jr. to the Honorable E. G. Shaffer 1959 February 5, 1 item (Box-folder 1:66)
      The Attorney General wrote to the Commonwealth's Attorney (for Wytheville, Virginia) that there were currently no enforceable laws for compulsory attendance.
    - Letter from George W. Holmes III to Dean Ralph Cherry 1959 February 12, 1 item (Box-folder 1:67)
      The letter describes map boundaries between Venable and Jefferson School and overcrowding of schools but the actual map is not present.
    - Letters from Davis Y. Paschall to Dr. E. J. Oglesby, and Mrs. Lester A. Wilson, Jr. President, Venable PTA about cancelling his address on the Tuition Grant Program 1959 February 13-16, 3 items (Box-folder 1:68)
    - Letter from the Commonwealth of Virginia Division of Statutory Research inviting Fendall R. Ellis to attend a meeting of The Committee on Enrollment and Transfers 1959 February 20, 1 item (Box-folder 1:69)
    - Correspondence between Governor James Lindsay Almond, Jr. and Fendall R. Ellis 1959 March 2, 3, 2 items (Box-folder 1:70)
      Superintendent Ellis wrote to Governor Almond congratulating him for his "outstanding leadership" in the "school crisis." Governor Almond responded that "the road ahead is most difficult." He also wrote that he felt that efforts were being made to "abolish public education in Virginia."
    - Letters between the Office of John S. Battle, Jr. and Fendall R. Ellis inviting him to attend a conference 1959 March 5, 2 items (Box-folder 1:71)
      Battle invited Dr. Ellis to attend the National Conference of Public School Officials and the United States Commission on Civil Rights in Nashville but Dr. Ellis was not able to attend.
    - Letters from Fendall R. Ellis to L. D. Cooley and Dr. Henry Cheetham, Minister of the Thomas Jefferson Memorial Unitarian Church 1959 April 27, 2 items (Box-folder 1:72)
      Dr. Ellis mentioned his gratitude for their meetings with "Negro" citizens and their work in "ameliorating the school problem and in improving race relations."
    - Letter from Louise R. Cooper, NAACP, to the parents of seventh graders announcing that schools are desegregated 1959 April 28, 1 item (Box-folder 1:73)
    - Letter from Fendall R. Ellis to Knox Turnbull thanking him for his leadership 1959 May 1, 1 item (Box-folder 1:74)
    - Correspondence between Fendall R. Ellis and Colonel Francis Pickens Miller thanking him for his essay 1959 May 4, 4 items (Box-folder 1:75)
      Colonel Miller wrote an essay "Rough Notes on Some Events in Charlottesville, Virginia (1957-1959)" which is included, and describes a group of local businessmen and University of Virginia leaders who made a statement of acceptance for desegregation with over twelve hundred signatures (published in The Daily Progress on January 31, 1959.) Pickens invited John S. Battle, Jr. but he responded that he "would have nothing to do with it." "…he was tired of the whole business."
    - Letter from Fendall R. Ellis to the Principals regarding pupil assignments and a list of grades and pupil assignments 1959 May 15, May 21, 2 items (Box-folder 1:76)
      Ellis asked principals to send him any information on pupils who should be transferred.
    - Letter from Fendall R. Ellis to Colonel Francis Pickens Miller about pupil assignments 1959 June 3, 1 item (Box-folder 1:77)
      Dr. Ellis was concerned that there would be a lot of requests for transfers and he was trying to maintain peace between the racial extremists and the NAACP.
    - Letters from Fendall R. Ellis to Randolph White, school assignments, and a press release 1959 June 9, 4 items (Box-folder 1:78)
      "School Assignments of Certain Negro Pupils for Session 1959-1960." Individuals that were named in the court case are listed along with the school they were attending in the next session.
    - Letters from Fendall R. Ellis and Colonel Francis Pickens Miller to Randolph L. White asking him to write an editorial encouraging the parents to accept school assignments 1959 June 16, 2 items (Box-folder 1:79)
      Colonel Miller and Dr. Ellis wanted parents to accept school assignments because they were concerned that transfers would upset racial extremists. Colonel Miller asked Randolph White to write an editorial stating that the assignments would be made according to Judge John Paul's Order.
    - Letter from Fendall R. Ellis to J. G. Blount revealing the teacher salaries during the closing of the schools 1959 June 22, 1 item (Box-folder 1:80)
    - Correspondence Sarah Patton Boyle to Fendall R. Ellis and John S. Battle, Jr. 1959 June 26, 2 items (Box-folder 1:81)
      Sarah Patton Boyle wrote to Ellis and Battle informing them that the NAACP was a moderate law abiding organization compared to "real radicals and trouble makers among Negroes" without leadership. There is a also a copy of The Augusta Courier
    - Letter from Fendall R. Ellis to James E. Bowen, Jr. 1959 July 1, 1 item (Box-folder 1:82)
      The letter has instructions for submitting a bill for teachers' salaries to the Commonwealth during the period September 1958 through January 1959.
    - Letter from W. T. Woodson to Fendall R. Ellis about desegregation in Fairfax, Virginia 1959 July 1, 1 item (Box-folder 1:83)
      Dr. Woodson, Division Superintendent of the Fairfax County School Board thanked Dr. Ellis for his help with desegregation in the Fairfax schools.
    - Letter from Fendall R. Ellis to Dr. Ralph W. Cherry and a letter from George W. Holmes III to Ellis about an honorarium for them for their assistance on the map of school districts 1959 July 2-3, 2 items (Box-folder 1:84)
    - Letter from Fendall R. Ellis to T. C. Williams about desegregation in Alexandria, Virginia 1959 August 28, 1 item (Box-folder 1:85)
    - Letters from Fendall R. Ellis to Colonel Francis Pickens Miller and Knox Turnbull about enrollment and pupil progress and a response from Colonel Miller 1959 October, 3 items (Box-folder 1:86)
      Dr. Ellis sent enrollment figures for the first day of school compared with the last sessions and a report on pupil progress. The statistics and enrollment information are not included.
    - Correspondence of Fendall R. Ellis and Eugene Williams, President NAACP Charlottesville Branch 1960 May 10, 23, 3 items (Box-folder 1:87)
      President Williams criticized Ellis for not instituting desegregation and not following the plan laid out by the U. S. Court of Appeals for the Fourth Circuit. Ellis responded that the School Board would assign pupils according to the desegregation plan. There is also a handwritten note that Mr. Williams "might not have brought suit if a Negro had been appointed to School Board."
    - Letter from Oliver W. Hill to the School Board of Charlottesville about an appeal on denied transfers for fifteen of Hills' clients 1960 June 24, 1 item (Box-folder 1:88)
    - Letter from Fendall R. Ellis to Oliver W. Hill about pupil assignments 1960 July 1, 1 item (Box-folder 1:89)
      Superintendent Ellis sent Hill information on pupil assignments for students named in the lawsuit. He also sent names of students that the School Board had approved for transfers.
    - Letter from Oliver W. Hill to Fendall R. Ellis requesting the names and addresses of "white" children in the Jefferson School District for the Hearing of Allen, et al vs. School Board of Prince Edward County, et al and a letter from Ellis requesting names from the Principals; list of names 1960 August 3, 4, 5 items (Box-folder 1:90)
    - Letters between Judge John Paul and Fendall R. Ellis regarding academic data for one of the appellants 1960 August 10, 11, 2 items (Box-folder 1:91)
      Judge John Paul requested Superintendent Ellis to send the academic data for Gloria Hamilton, a " Negro" applicant for transfer to Lane High School. Superintendent Ellis indicated that she would struggle in eighth grade at Lane.
    - Letter from E. L. Lamberth to Fendall R. Ellis thanking him for a copy of the Charlottesville school desegregation plan 1960 September 9, 1 item (Box-folder 1:92)
    - Letters from Mrs. Hattie L. DeBerry to Fendall R. Ellis requesting permission for her son, Garwin DeBerry to transfer from Lane High School to Jackson P. Burley High School 1960 September 23; 1962 June 16, 19, 3 items (Box-folder 1:93)
      Mrs. DeBerry wanted her son, Garwin DeBerry to transfer to Burley because he was not allowed to play athletics at Lane and it was his intention to make athletics his "life career." [Garwin DeBerry became the head football coach at Charlottesville High School for twenty eight years from 1980 to 2007 following Tommy Theodose. He led the Charlottesville Black Knights into victory, winning multiple Jefferson District titles.]
    - Letter from the court reporter to Fendall R. Ellis 1960 September 23, 1 item (Box-folder 1:94)
      The court reporter of the United States District Court Western District of Virginia, Mary Bidle, wrote to Superintendent Ellis that the transcript was finished and that she hoped that "as the years go by your problems will vanish."
    - Letters between Fendall R. Ellis and John S. Battle, Jr. about Battle continuing to represent the School Board 1960 September 28, October 5, 2 items (Box-folder 1:95)
    - Letter from Virginia E. Lewis to Fendall R. Ellis and a list of school divisions 1960 October 12, 2 items (Box-folder 1:96)
    - Letter from Fendall R. Ellis to other school superintendents in Virginia suggesting that they meet to exchange information about desegregation 1960 October 20, 1 item (Box-folder 1:97)
    - Letters between Fendall R. Ellis and John S. Battle about the appendix filed in the case of Carolyn M. Dodson et al. vs. The School Board of the City of Charlottesville, et al. (appendix not present) 1961 January 9, 2 items (Box-folder 1:98)
    - Letters between Fendall R. Ellis and John S. Battle, Jr. regarding the date of the hearing before the United States Court of Appeals in Richmond 1961 January 20, 2 items (Box-folder 1:99)
      Superintendent Ellis wrote that the weather made it impossible for him to attend.
    - Correspondence between Fendall R. Ellis and L. O. Todd about a copy of Charlottesville's desegregation plan 1961 February 28, 2 items (Box-folder 1:100)
    - Correspondence between John S. Battle, Jr. and Fendall R. Ellis about pupil assignments 1961 March 1, 22, 2 items (Box-folder 1:101)
      Dr. Ellis asked John S. Battle if the schools should take any action regarding the regulations issued by the State Board of Education and Battle responded that they should wait until they have heard the decision from the United States Court for the Fourth Circuit.
    - Letter from John S. Battle, Jr. to Fendall R. Ellis and the Decision of the United States Court of Appeals for the Fourth Circuit in the Carolyn M. Dodson case 1961 April 20, 2 items (Box-folder 1:102)
      The Court affirmed the ruling of the District Court saying that the School Board was taking steps to end discriminatory practices.
    - Letters from Fendall R. Ellis to Principals and School Board members asking them to study the U. S. Circuit Court of Appeals Decision 1961 April 25, 27, 3 items (Box-folder 1:103)
    - Letter from Fendall R. Ellis to John S. Battle, Jr. and form letters for pupil assignments in elementary schools 1961 May 3, 2 items (Box-folder 1:104)
      Dr. Ellis sought Mr. Battle's advice on the wording of the application forms for pupil assignments in the elementary schools.
    - Letter from Fendall R. Ellis to Adam Clymer about Clymer's article on private schools in The Virginian-Pilot (article not present) 1961 May 25, 1 item (Box-folder 1:105)
    - Letter from Fendall R. Ellis to John S. Battle, Jr. and pupil assignment preferences 1961 June 6, 13, 2 items (Box-folder 1:106)
      Dr. Ellis interviewed the parents of the forty four "Negro" children living outside of the Jefferson School District and assigned them to the schools of the parent's choice. Twelve children were assigned to Venable High School and thirty two were assigned to Jefferson School for the school year 1961-1962.
    - Correspondence between a parent and Fendall R. Ellis about the enrollment of her daughter 1961 June 18, 22 and 1962 June 19, 3 items (Box-folder 1:107)
      Dr. Ellis responded that he looked forward to meeting her to discuss the enrollment of her daughter. Later he wrote that she could attend Jackson P. Burley High School. (June 19, 1962)
    - Letters from John S. Battle, Jr. to Fendall R. Ellis regarding their upcoming appeal in Allen v. School Board of the City of Charlottesville 1961 September 5, 17, 2 items (Box-folder 1:108)
      John Battle made his arguments to Judge Paul and wrote that the Judge "has now a reasonably sympathetic attitude towards our endeavors."
    - Correspondence between James Baker and Fendall R. Ellis and enrollment figures for The News Leader1961 September 12, 4 items (Box-folder 1:109)
      Dr. Ellis responded that there were five hundred and twenty five "white" pupils and twenty "Negro" pupils at Venable and nine hundred and ninety "white" pupils and fifteen "Negro" pupils at Lane. Dr. Ellis explained that the decision from the Circuit Court of Appeals might change some of the figures. A questionnaire is mentioned but not present.
    - Correspondence between the Honorable James M. Thomson and Fendall R. Ellis answering questions about how the schools were closed 1961 October 17, 2 items (Box-folder 1:110)
    - Correspondence between Fendall R. Ellis and Dr. Cleveland A. Thomas about enrollment at Parker School in Chicago 1961 October 17, 30, 2 items (Box-folder 2:1)
      Dr. Ellis asked Dr. Thomas, Principal of Francis W. Parker School about the percentage of students that were "Negro."
    - Correspondence between Fendall R. Ellis, J. G. Blount and John S. Battle, Jr. about establishing compulsory attendance and pupil assignments 1961 October-November, 11 items (Box-folder 2:2)
      Attorney John S. Battle, Jr. recommended that they hold off on implementing a compulsory school attendance resolution until after the hearings.
    - Correspondence between John S. Battle, Jr., Judge John Paul and Fendall R. Ellis and a Motion to Intervene 1961 November, 4 items (Box-folder 2:3)
      S. W. Tucker filed a Motion to Intervene for students that he wanted to add to the lawsuit. Judge Paul ruled that no action be taken because there was no point in transferring students during the school year.
    - Letter from Fendall R. Ellis to the parents of Vernetta Lewis, and Vernetta Lewis to her teacher 1961 November, 1962 June 8, 2 items (Box-folder 2:4)
      Dr. Ellis wrote to her parents that she could attend Jackson P. Burley High School in the 1962-1963 school sessions. In November 1961 Vernetta Lewis had written to her teacher, "I don't like Lane and nothing about it. I don't feel that I belong here. Maybe I don't." She also mentioned that the boy that sat in front of her was calling her names and kicking her.
    - Correspondence between John S. Battle, Jr. Judge John Paul, and Fendall R. Ellis and a Motion to Vacate the Stay 1962 March -April, 9 items (Box-folder 2:5)
      Battle described the plaintiff's motion (which was overruled) as a "back door effort" to have "Negro" children placed in Lane for the 1962-1963 session." Battle recommended that the School Board stay firm on using academic criteria but transfer the Woodfolk twins into Lane to appease the Court.
    - Letter from Fendall R. Ellis to J. M. Dunnavant, Jr. and a pupil transfer form for "white" children who live in the Jefferson School District 1962 May 9, 2 items (Box-folder 2:6)
    - Letters between Fendall R. Ellis, J. M. Dunnavant, Jr. and Mrs. Josephine Morrison about transferring her daughter from Jefferson to Venable School 1962 May 30, June 4, August 30, October 22, 4 items (Box-folder 2:7)
      Mrs. Morrison, a client of S. W. Tucker wrote, "I want my child to attend a desegregated school as she is entitle [sic] to do under the Constitution." Dr. Ellis denied the request because the Court had ruled that pupils must attend the elementary school that was in their district. The ruling was under appeal and on October 22, Dr. Ellis wrote that since the Court did change its ruling, her daughter could attend Venable School.